Preliminary Guide to the District of Columbia Council Records, 1968-1975 MS2080
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
District of Columbia Council records
1968-1975
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2080
32 Linear Feet
Collection consists of District Council considerations, hearings, proposals, correspondence, subject files, legislation, magnetic tapes, and budget files. The collection ranges in date from 1968 to 1975 and they cover the District Council of Washington, D.C.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Acquisition data is unknown.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Council of the District of Columbia is the legislative branch of the District government. All legislative powers are vested in the Council. In addition, the council approves the District's annual budget and financial plan, and sets the revenue required to fund the budget. It oversees the programs and operations of government agencies, and acts on or initiates reorganization plans for the Executive Branch. The Council determines land use, through the adoption of the comprehensive plan, and undertakes redistricting based on the decennial census. In addition, the Council appoints members to certain boards and commissions, and must confirm major appointments made by the Mayor.
The Council develops legislative initiatives and budget priorities to promote the public welfare. It oversees the performance of government agencies and the implementation of management reforms to improve service delivery. Council committees issue analytical reports on the effectiveness of government operations and make recommendations for reform. In addition, the Council monitors agency spending to ensure compliance with the approved budget and financial plan.
As the local elected representative body, the Council seeks citizen participation throughout the legislative process. It holds public hearings to provide an opportunity for public comment on proposed legislation, policy initiatives and government operations. Also, the Council helps citizens access government information and services.
The Council is composed of thirteen Members: a representative elected from each of the eight wards and five members, including the Chairman, elected at-large. The Council conducts its work through standing committees and special committees established as needed. Council staff perform legislative research, bill drafting, program and policy analysis, and constituent services. In addition, the Council is supported by centralized administrative, legal and budget offices.
To assist in its oversight, the Council appoints the D.C. Auditor who conducts statutorily required audits of government accounts and operation, and other audits as directed by the Council.
Much of the work of the Council is done in standing committees and special committees. Committees are established at the first meeting of each Council period.
To hold the office of Member of the Council, a person must be a registered voter, a resident of the District for at least a year prior to the general election, and of the ward if nominated for election from a particular ward, and hold no other public office for which compensation beyond expenses is received. A member is elected from each of the District's eight wards, and four members are elected at-large to serve a four-year term.
Taken from the DC Council website 2005.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consists of Council of the District of Columbia considerations, hearings, proposals, correspondence, subject files, legislation, magnetic tapes, and budget files. The collection ranges in date from 1968 to 1975 and they cover the District Council of Washington, D.C.
Please note: this collection contains unprocessed materials. Ask staff about using this material.
Arrangement
This collection is not processed and series have not yet been decided upon. The current arrangement reflects the arrangement when donated.
General
This collection is not processed. Some of these box descriptions may not be entirely accurate. Please allow extra time when using this collection for research.
Legislation; Budget; Washington (D.C.); District of Columbia. City Council
- Hearings, Proposals Eisenhower Center - Environment, undated (Box 1)
- Hearings, Proposals Environment - Hearings, undated (Box 2)
- Hearings, Proposals Hearings, undated (Box 3)
- Hearings, Proposals Hearings, undated (Box 4)
- Hearings, Proposals Health Related, undated (Box 5)
- Hearings, Proposals Health Related - Housing, undated (Box 6)
- Hearings, Proposals Housing, undated (Box 7)
- Hearings, Proposals Housing, undated (Box 8)
- Hearings, Proposals Housing - Public Safety, undated (Box 9)
- Hearings, Proposals Public Safety, undated (Box 10)
- Hearings, Proposals Public Safety, undated (Box 11)
- Hearings, Proposals Public Safety, undated (Box 12)
- Hearings, Proposals Personnel - Rape, undated (Box 13)
- Hearings, Proposals Register - Reports (Court), undated (Box 14)
- Hearings, Proposals Regulations, undated (Box 15)
- Hearings, ProposalsRegulations, undated (Box 16)
- Hearings, Proposals Regulations - Transportation, undated (Box 17)
- Hearings, Proposals Transportation, undated (Box 18)
- Hearings, Proposals Transportation, undated (Box 19)
- Hearings, Proposals Transportation, undated (Box 20)
- Hearings, Proposals Transportation - Urban Renewal, undated (Box 21)
- Hearings, Proposals Urban Renewal, undated (Box 22)
- Hearings, Proposals Urban Renewal, undated (Box 24)
- Hearings, Proposals Urban Renewal, undated (Box 23)
- Hearings, Proposals Urban Renewal - Welfare, undated (Box 25)
- Hearings, Proposals Welfare Zoning, undated (Box 26)
- Hearings, Proposals Zoning, undated (Box 27)
- Hearings, Proposals Zoning, undated (Box 27A)
- Hearings, Proposals Miscellaneous, 1972-74 and undated materials (Box 28)
- Hearings, Proposals Miscellaneous, 1968-1971, undated (Box 29)
- Hearings, Proposals Cable Television, undated (Box 30)
- Hearings, Proposals Council of Governments (COG), undated (Box 31)
- Hearings, Proposals Council of Governments (COG), undated (Box 32)
- Correspondence, 1970 (Box 53)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box 54)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box 55)
- Correspondence, 1972 (Box 56)
- Correspondence, 1973 (Box 57)
- Correspondence, 1974, 1970-1974 (Box 58)
- Correspondence, unsorted by year, 1969- circa 1970 (Box 39)
- Correspondence, unsorted by year, undated (Box 41)
- Agency reports and Council statements, undated (Box 40)
- Subject Files, Abortion, undated (Box 42)
- Subject Files, Airports - Clothes for Kids, undated (Box 43)
- Subject Files, Commercial Development - Education, undated (Box 44 (currently missing))
- Subject Files, Elections - Human Rights Law, undated (Box 45)
- Subject Files, Identification Cards - Property Taxes, undated (Box 46)
- Subject Files, Reading is Fun - Statistics Miscellaneous, undated (Box 47)
- Subject Files, Tax Relief for Elderly - Women, undated (Box 48)
- Legislative Research Agenda Book - Corporation Council Opinions (Abortion), undated (Box 49)
- Legislative Research District of Columbia Committee: House of Representatives - Legislative Programs: General, undated (Box 50)
- Legislative Research Legislative Programs: General - Legislative Research: Briefs, Memos, Reports, Regulations, Resolutions, undated (Box 51)
- Legislative Research News Releases - Vice Chairman's Office Legislation, undated (Box 52)
- Budget: Accounting, Vouchers 1970: Travel, Communication - 1972: Equipment, 1970-1972 (Box 33)
- Budget: Accounting, Vouchers 1973: Appropriation/Allotment - 1973: Telephone, Communication (Box 34)
- Budget: General Preparation Materials ***-1969: Miscellaneous - 1971: Miscellaneous, 1969-1971 (Box 35)
- Budget: General Preparation Materials 1972-1973: Council Meeting on Budget -: Budget Hearings (Box 36)
- Budget: General Preparation Materials 1974: DC Schools - 1975: Community Review, 1974-1975 (Box 37)
- Budget: General, 1974-1975 (Box 38)
- Miscellaneous/Unidentified, undated (Box 59)
- Miscellaneous/Unidentified, undated (Box 60)
- Magnetic Tapes of District of Columbia City Council Regular Meetings, undated (Box 61)
- Magnetic Tapes of District of Columbia City Council Regular Meetings, undated (Box 62)
- Miscellaneous/Unidentified, undated (Box 63)
- Miscellaneous Financial/Budget Records, undated (Box 64)